[MUSIC]
[음악]
So this notion of collaborative filtering is that somehow we wanna leverage
협업 필터링이란 다른 사람의 구매 이력을
what other people have purchased.
활용하는 개념을 말합니다
And the case of product recommendation or other links more generically between
상품 추천이나 사용자와 품목 사이의 관련성을 고려해서
users and items, to make recommendations for other users.
다른 사용자들에게 추천합니다
And so it seems very intuitive that when we're thinking about doing product
상품을 추천하려고 할 때
recommendation that we wanna build in information like
사용자가 이 품목을 사면
if a person bought this item, then
다른 품목에도 관심이 있기 마련인데
they're probably also interested in some other item because we've seen lots and
과거에도 사람들이 이런 품목들을 함께
lots of examples in the past of people buying those pairs of items together.
사는 모습을 많이 봐왔기 때문입니다
Maybe not simultaneously, at the same time, but
동시에는 아니더라도
in the course of their purchase histories.
구매 이력 어딘가에서요
Okay, so this brings us to the idea of co-occurrence of purchases.
이렇게 구매의 동시발생이란 개념으로 이어집니다
So, for example, if I was just on Amazon, buying diapers, well, we've probably
아마존에서 기저귀를 사는데 기저귀 사는
seen lots of examples of people who bought diapers also bought baby wipes.
수많은 사람들이 아기 물티슈를 함께 구입했다고 할게요
Okay, so how can we use this type of co-occurrence of
이런 구매의 동시발생을 어떻게
purchases to make recommendations?
활용할 수 있을까요?
[SOUND] Okay [LAUGH] so let's talk about this co-occurrence
[소리] 예 [웃음] 이제부터 만들 동시발생 행렬에 대해
matrix that we're gonna build up.
알아볼게요
And this is gonna store all of our information about which purchases
사람들이 함께 구매한 목록의 정보를
people bought together.
모두 저장합니다
And again, when I say together I don't mean simultaneously,
다시 한번 강조하자면 동시가 아니라
just together at some point in their history of purchases.
구매 이력의 어느 시점에서입니다.
So I'm gonna build up this Matrix C and this matrix is an items by items matrix.
행렬 C를 구성할 텐데 항목-항목 행렬입니다
Okay, so we're gonna list all the different items for
이 행렬의 행에 있는 모든 항목을
our rows of this matrix.
열거하겠습니다
And likewise, all the different items, for the columns.
마찬가지로 열의 모든 항목을 열거합니다
So, for example, maybe this row of this matrix,
예를 들어 행렬의 이 행은
might be the row corresponding to diapers.
기저귀에 해당할지도 모르지요
And then if this is lets say the third row of this matrix,
이게 행렬의 세 번째 행이고
then I would also have that the third column of this
세 번째 열 또한
matrix Corresponds to diapers as well.
기저귀에 대응하게 만듭니다
Okay, and so if I want to say that many people purchased diapers and baby wipes,
많은 사람들이 기저귀와 아기 물티슈를 샀으면
let's look at the row for diapers and then we scroll over to the column for,
기저귀 행을 본 다음 스크롤해서
let's say this column here, is for baby wipes.
아기 물티슈 열로 넘어갑니다
And in this entry, of this matrix there's some number entered.
이 항에 숫자가 있네요
And that number represents the number of people.
숫자는 사람 수를 뜻합니다
Purchasing both diapers and baby wipes.
기저귀와 아기 물티슈를 모두 구입한 사람들이요
Okay, well, let me ask you a question.
여기서 퀴즈 하나 내죠
Is the number of people who purchased diapers and baby wipes
기저귀와 아기 물티슈를 동시에 산 사람 수와
the same as the number of people who purchased baby wipes and diapers?
아기 물티슈와 기저귀를 동시에 산 사람 수가 같나요?
Yes, so we would go to the baby wipes row.
그렇죠 아기 물티슈 행으로 갑니다
And this diapers column and
이게 기저귀 열인데
notice that this is the exactly same number, okay?
숫자가 정확히 같은 게 보이시죠?
And so what this means is this a symmetric matrix that,
대칭행렬이란 뜻이니
if we look across the diagonal here, Then we're gonna see a reflection.
여기 대각선을 그으면 대칭을 이룹니다
If we took this matrix and folded it across that little diagonal line I
이 행렬을 대각선을 따라 접으면
just drew you would get exactly the same numbers matching up.
정확히 같은 숫자끼리 겹쳐집니다
Okay, and just to reiterate the way we're gonna build up this co-occurrence matrix,
이 동시발생 행렬 구축하는 법을 다시 보기 위해
is we're gonna search through all the user's history of purchases they've made,
모든 사용자의 구매 이력을 검색해
and count.
수를 셉니다
And every time we see a purchase of diapers we'll add
기저귀 구매가 있을 때마다 기저귀에 더하고
of diapers along with all the other items, we're gonna add one to that entry,
다른 항목에 대해서도 똑같이 합니다
and we're gonna keep incrementing that matrix as we're searching over users.
사용자를 살펴보면서 행렬을 증가시키는 거죠
Okay, but now let's talk about how we're gonna use this co-occurrence matrix
동시발생 행렬로 어떻게 추천할지
in order to make recommendations.
말씀드리죠
And it's really, really straight forward.
아주 간단합니다
So let's say that a user has just purchased diapers, and
사용자가 방금 기저귀를 샀다고 하고
I wanna make some recommendation for them.
뭔가 추천을 해주려고 합니다
Well what I'm gonna do is I'm gonna look at the diapers row of this matrix,
행렬의 기저귀 행에 가서
so if we go back, to that, C matrix here,
다시 돌아가 행렬 C를 보면
I'm gonna grab out this diapers row, and I'm just gonna draw that row here.
기저귀 행만 골라서 여기 그립니다
And what this row has is how often people bought diapers and,
그러면 이 행은 사람들이 기저귀와 함께 사는 물품들,
remember, baby wipes was one of the items.
아기 물티슈가 물품 중 하나였죠
Oops, sorry, not baby items, baby wipes.
죄송합니다 아기용품이 아니라 아기 물티슈네요
And that has, let's say a 100 counts.
총 100개라고 할게요
And then there's also let's say pacifiers.
그리고 고무 젖꼭지도 있다고 할게요
And maybe there are 4 counts of pacifiers.
고무 젖꼭지는 4개 있습니다
Let's think of something else.
다른 게 뭐가 있을까요
So let's say that there's some DVD, let's say there's no counts of those DVDs.
DVD가 있다고 할게요 DVD는 같이 사지 않았습니다
We're gonna have this whole vector of counts of how many times people
이 벡터는 기저귀를 산 사람들이
who bought diapers, bought all these other products.
다른 상품을 얼마나 샀는지 나타냅니다
Using this,
이걸 사용하면
now we can very straightforwardly make our recommendations.
아주 간단하게 추천을 할 수 있죠
All we do is we sort this vector and
이 벡터를 정렬해서
recommend the items with the largest counts.
가장 카운트가 큰 물품을 추천하면 됩니다
So maybe, we'll recommend baby wipes, and milk, and baby food, and
기저귀를 막 산 사람에게는 아마
things like this for somebody who just purchased diapers.
아기 물티슈, 우유, 이유식 같은 걸 추천하겠네요
[MUSIC]
[음악]